Preliminary Guide to the Pre-1870 Newspaper Collection, 1833-1885
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pre-1870 Newspaper collection 1833-1885
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
16 linear feet Extent: 900 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00945
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Transferred from Perkins Library to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1997 and 1998.
Collection Overview
Recent uncataloged accessions of Pre-1870 newspapers, transferred from Perkins Library to the Rare Book Manuscript and Special Collections Library at Duke University in 1997 and 1998. The bulk of this collection consists of papers published in the South during the Civil War, but several newspapers from Northern states are also included. The papers in this collection are very fragile and should be used with extreme care. Please consult with reference staff prior to photocopying.
Subject Headings
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents of Collection
- Newspaper Collection
  Uncataloged pre-1870 newspapers received in1996 from the Serials Department of Perkins Library. Dates range from 1830-1887,with the bulk of the issues published from1861 to1869. The majority originate from North Carolina cities, but the states of Massachusetts, New York, South Carolina, Mississippi, Kentucky, Pennsylvania, and Maine are also represented. Newspapers are in numbered folders. Many are very fragile: handle with extreme care on a spacious, flat surface. Reference staff must be consulted before any photocopying is done.
  - Roanoke News, Weldon, NC: 1869,23 Oct.-25 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Friend of Temperance, Raleigh, NC: 1869,20 Mar. (Box 1)
  - Friend of Temperance, Raleigh, NC: 1869,2 Apr.-22 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Friend of Temperance, Raleigh, NC: 1869,29 Sept.-22 Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1861,26 Mar.-4 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1861,11 June-20 Aug (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1861,27 Aug.-1 Oct.;1862,5 Feb., 29 July, 14 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Weekly Sentinel, Raleigh, NC: 1867, 17 Dec.-31 Dec.; 1869,16 Mar., 8 June-6 July (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Weekly Sentinel, Raleigh, NC: 1869, 3 Aug., 16 Nov.; 1867, 12 Mar.-2 Apr., 16 Apr.-21 May, 4 June, 18 June-25 June (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Weekly Sentinel, Raleigh, NC: 1867, 2 July-10 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Weekly Sentinel, Raleigh, NC: 1867, 24 Sept.-19 Nov., 3 Dec.-10 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Weekly News, Charlotte, NC: 1869,30 Nov.-21 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Weekly State Journal, Raleigh, NC: 1860,12 Dec.; 1861, 2 Jan., 16 Jan., 27 Feb., 20 Mar.-3 Apr., 24 Apr. (Box 2)
  - The Weekly State Journal, Raleigh, NC: 1861, 22 May, 10 July, 31 July-21 Aug., 4 Sept.-11 Sept., 25 Sept.-2 Oct., 30 Oct.-6 Nov., 4 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Weekly State Journal, Raleigh, NC: 1862, 25 June; 9 July; 23 July; 24 Sept.; 1863, 22 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1863, 21 July, 10 Nov.; 1866,10 July-7 Aug. (Box 2)
  - Mecklenburg Jeffersonian, Charlotte, NC: 1844, 27 Jan.-1848, 12 July (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mecklenburg Jeffersonian, Charlotte, NC: 1842,15 Mar.-1843, 24 Oct (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mecklenburg Jeffersonian, Charlotte, NC: 1841,9 Mar.-1842, 8 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Milton Chronicle, Milton, NC: 1844,22 May-1863, 9 Nov. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Milton Gazette, Milton, NC: 1830,21 Aug.-1831, 21 Jan. (Box 3)
  - Milton Spectator, Milton, NC: 1832,31 Oct.-1836, 27 Sept. (Box 3)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1866,24 July, 14 Aug.-20 Nov. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1866,27 Nov.-1867, 5 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1867,12 Mar.-7 May (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Weldon Patriot, Weldon, NC: 1856,13 Nov., 6 Nov., 16 May (Box 3)
  - Louisburg Union and North Carolina Miscellany, Louisburg, NC: 1847,19 Aug.-4 Nov. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Wilmington Post and Semi-Weekly Post, Wilmington, NC: 1868,9 July, 18 Oct.; 1869, 16 Dec. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New Bern Journal of Commerce, New Bern, NC: 1867,13 Sept. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Message, Greensboro, NC: 1869,15 Sept. (Box 4)
  - The Morning Star, Wilmington, NC: 1868,29 Sept., 31 Dec.; 1869,5 Jan., 29 Jan., 19 Feb., 23 Mar. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Mercury, Raleigh, NC: 1864,30 Apr.-29 Oct. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Morning Star, Wilmington, NC: 1869,24 Mar.-22 Sept. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    NOTE: Box 5 consists of two bound volumes and is heavy.
  - The Morning Star, Wilmington, NC: 1868,27 Mar.-22 Sept (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Morning Star, Wilmington, NC: 1869,23 Sept.-1870, 22 Mar (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1859,19 Apr.-28 June (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1859,5 July-16 Aug. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1859,23 Aug.;1860,10 Jan.-13 Mar. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1860,20 Mar.-19 June (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1860,26 June-25 Sept. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1860,2 Oct.-22 Dec. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1861,1 Jan.-19 Mar. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Little Adder, Salisbury, NC: 1860,8 June-1860, 13 July (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Lincoln Republican, Lincolnton, NC: 1841,1 Sept. (Box 6)
  - Microcosm, Raleigh, NC: 1838,30 June-1841, 17 July (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Chiefly bound, but some issues are loose.
  - The Live Giraffe, Raleigh, NC: 1852,27 Mar.-1859, 7 May (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Eagle, Fayetteville, NC: 1868,28 Aug.-16 Nov. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Eagle, Fayetteville, NC: 1868,19 Nov.-31 Dec. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - The Eagle, Fayetteville, NC: 1869,7 Jan.-8 July (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - The Eagle, Fayetteville, NC: 1869,29 July-23 Dec. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1865,4 Jan.1865,1 Feb.-8 Mar.1866,10 Jan.-30 May (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1866,6 June-17 Oct. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1866,24 Oct., 31 Oct.1866,14 Nov.-26 Dec.1867,2 Jan.-13 Feb. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1867,13 Feb.-26 June (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1867,10 July-25 Dec. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1868,22 Jan.-23 Dec. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1869,13 Jan.-7 July (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - North Carolina Presbyterian, Fayetteville, NC: 1869,21 July-29 Dec. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Forest Weekly Register, Forest, Mass.: 1869,9 Jan.-20 Oct. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The Weekly Clarion, Jackson, Miss.: 1869,28 Oct. (Box 9)
  - Brooklyn Daily Eagle, Brooklyn, NY: 1869,5 May (Box 9)
  - Examiner and Chronicle, New York, NY: 1867,15 Aug. (Box 9)
  - Watchman and Reflector, Boston, Mass.: 1867,28 Nov.-16 Dec. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Gloucester Telegraph, Gloucester, Mass.: 1866,1 Sept.-29 April (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Gloucester Telegraph, Gloucester, Mass.: 1868, 2 May-1869, 6 Jan. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Essex County Mercury, Salem, Mass.: 1864,20 July - 1865, 2 Aug. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Boston Weekly Transcript, Boston, Mass.: 1869,22 June (Box 9)
  - Gloucester Telegraph, Gloucester, Mass.: 1869,9 Jan.-13 Mar. (Box 9)
  - Gloucester Telegraph, Gloucester, Mass.: 1869,17 Mar.-1 Sept. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The South, New York, NY: 1884, Aug.-1887, Mar. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Lynn Record, Lynn, Mass.: 1830,4 Sept. (Box 10)
  - The Voice of Masonry, Louisville, KY: 1859,1 Jan.-15 July (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - New York Day-Book, New York, NY: 1869,2 Jan.-28 Aug. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - New York Day-Book, New York, NY: 1869,4 Sept.-25 Dec. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - The Evening Telegraph, Philadelphia, Penn.: 1864,15 Feb. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Daily Republican, Charleston, SC: 1869,21 Oct., 23 Oct.; 1870,8 Feb. (Box 11)
  - The Abbeville Press and Banner, Abbeville, SC: 1869,15 Oct. (Box 11)
  - Saturday Night, Philadelphia, Penn.: 1865,2 Dec., 30 Dec. (Box 11)
  - Shoe Leather Reporter, Boston, Mass.: 1869,24 June (Box 11)
  - The Brunswick Telegraph, Brunswick, Maine: 1868,8 May-1869, 16 July (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Very fragile items. Some are fragments. Please ask staff to assist.
  - Danvers Gazette, Danvers, Mass.: 1868,4 April, 18 April, [23 April?], 2 May, 9 May (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - The Eagle, Fayetteville, NC: 1868,12 Aug.-27 Aug. Also Vol. 1, No. 14 (undated) (Box 11)
  - Weldon Patriot, Weldon, NC: 1859,10 Aug. (Box 11)
  - Weekly State Journal Raleigh, NC: 1862,20 Aug. (Box 11)
  - Weekly Sentinel, Raleigh, NC: 1868,7 July (Box 11)
  - Western Democrat, Charlotte, NC: 1861,12 Mar., 31 Dec. (Box 11)
  - North Carolinian, Elizabeth City, NC: 1869,23 Sept. (Box 11)
  - Weekly State Journal, Raleigh, NC: 1862,30 July (Box 11)
- Accession 1998-0268
  Uncataloged pre-1870 newspapers transferred form the Serials Department of Perkins Library to the Rubenstein Library in1998.The newspapers in this addition span1833 to1885,chiefly the1860s.The bulk of this addition are issues of the Memphis Daily Appeal, (Atlanta, GA) from 1862-1865.Newspapers from Texas, Vermont, and Tennessee are also included in this portion of the collection. The newspaper are in numbered folders. Many of the news paper are very fragile and should be used only on a large flat space. Consult with reference staff prior to photocopying.
  - The Memphis Daily Appeal - Atlanta, GA. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1964, Jan. 9 (Box 1)
    - 1864, May 6 (Box 1)
    - 1863, July 27 (Box 1)
    - 1863, June 29 (Box 1)
    - 1863, June 12 (Box 1)
    - 1862, Feb.1 (Box 1)
    - 1863, Mar. 14 (Box 1)
    - 1863, Mar. 21 (Box 1)
    - 1863, Mar. 26 (Box 1)
    - 1863, Mar. 23 (Box 1)
    - 1863, Apr. 3 (Box 1)
    - 1863, Apr. 4 (Box 1)
    - 1863, Apr. 13 (Box 1)
    - 1863, May 4 (Box 1)
    - 1968, Mar. 9 (Box 1)
    - 1862, Feb. 4-6 (Box 1)
  - Memphis Daily Appeal - Atlanta, GA. (Folder 2)
    - 1861, Aug. 29- 1862, Feb. 2 (Box 1)
    - 1862, Feb. 7 - 1862, Mar. 7 (Box 1)
  - Memphis Daily Appeal - Atlanta, GA. (Folder 3)
    - 1862, Mar. 9 - 1862, Apr. 17 (Box 1)
    - 1863, June 13- 1863, July 31 (Box 1)
  - The Daily Republican - Chattanooga, TN. (Folder 4)
    - 1869, Sept. 12 (Box 1)
  - The Knoxville Register - Knoxville, TN.
    - 1833, Apr. 24 (Box 1)
  - The Rio Grande Courier - Brownsville, TX..
    - 1866, Apr. 6 (Box 1)
  - Vermont Watchman and State Journal - Montpelier, VT.
    - 1859, Dec. 2 (Box 1)
  - The Dallas Morning News - Dallas, TX.
    - 1885, Oct. 1 (Box 1)
  - The Galveston News - Galveston, TX.
    - 1846, Mar. 3 (Box 1)